<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The state of Northampton from the beginning of the fire Sept. 20th 1675 to Nov. 5th represented in a letter to a friend in London and now recommended to all well disposed persons in order to Christian-charity and speedy relief for the said distressed town and people / by a country minister.</title>
            <author>Pearse, Edward, 1631-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12097</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13799093</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13799093</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101909</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56816)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101909)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 470:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The state of Northampton from the beginning of the fire Sept. 20th 1675 to Nov. 5th represented in a letter to a friend in London and now recommended to all well disposed persons in order to Christian-charity and speedy relief for the said distressed town and people / by a country minister.</title>
                  <author>Pearse, Edward, 1631-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson ... and William Cockeraine ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Letter signed E.P.</note>
                  <note>Written by Edward Pearse.  Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Wing apparently in error lists imprint as: For Jonathan Robinson and William Cockershow, 1675.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fires --  England --  Northampton (Northamptonshire)</term>
               <term>Northampton (England) --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101909:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101909:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE State of Northampton From the beginning of the FIRE, <hi>Sept.</hi> 20th 1675. to <hi>Nov.</hi> 5th.</p>
            <p>Repreſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed in a <hi>Letter</hi> to a FRIEND in LONDON; And now recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to all well diſpoſed Perſons, in order to Chriſtian-Charity, and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Relief for the ſaid diſtreſſed Town and People.</p>
            <p>By a Country Miniſter.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Licenſed,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Nov.</hi> 22. 1675.</date>
                           <signed>Roger L'eſtrange.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Lion</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard, and <hi>William Cookeraine</hi> Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller in <hi>NORTHAMPTON.</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101909:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101909:2"/>
            <head>THE State of Northamton FROM The beginning of the Fire, <hi>Sept.</hi> 20th. 1675. to <hi>Nov.</hi> the 5th. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I had not expected a true and full Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the beginning and Progreſs of the dreadful Fire at <hi>Northampton,</hi> as alſo of the Loſſes, State, and Relief of that diſtreſſed People, from a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and able hand, I ſhould have labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to have prepared this, ſuch as it is, ſooner for your ſatisfaction. I do not pretend to inform you with every Circumſtance and Accident, that's not to be looked for; Becauſe I know none that had ſo much leiſure from their own or other Mens Conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nments, as to obſerve and trace the Motions of that terrible Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which was that day carried up and down upon the Wings of a ſtrong and violent Wind. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, I find in mine own diligent enquiry, even of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Men, that it is as impoſſible for a Man who imploys all his endeavours to ſave his own Goods and Life in one part of a Street, to tell me when and in what Houſe the Fire brake out in another place di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101909:3"/>from him, as it is for a Soldier, whoſe Life is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in a narrow particular Station, to relate what was out of his ſight, done in every Wing, in every Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Troop or Company, much more in every Rank and File of the whole Army, at once engaged and ſpread over all the Field, as this Fire was ſpread over the Body, and all parts of the Town. The All-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eye of the Lord of theſe mighty Hoſts of Fire and Wind, can give an exact and perfect Story of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular Action of that fatal Day. No one Man can, nor many Men apart, becauſe they were not in every place, nor obſerved all things, but as each one gives in his Obſervation; which muſt be gathered together to make a Story, ſo it muſt be taken up. And this I aſſure you, that I gathered theſe following paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, as well as I was able, and from perſons as able to inform me, and as diſtinctly related, as can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from perſons under the diſorders of Care, Fear, and Amazement at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>That I may repreſent <hi>Northampton</hi> in its Ruines, it may not be amiſs to preſent the Figure and Scituation of it as it ſtood and flouriſhed;<note place="margin">A Deſcription of the Town.</note> becauſe ſome may peruſe theſe lines, that knew it not, and the better conceive the courſe of the Fire, which I ſhall ſhew you, and the great alteration of it, from a Beautiful Town, to Pitts and Rubbiſh. <hi>Northampton</hi> might well contend with the beſt Inland-City or Town, that is not ſeated upon a Navigable River, for ſweet and wholſom Air, pleaſantneſs of Scituation, plenty and cheapneſs of Corn and Butchers Meat, good ancient Buildings, dry and commodious Cellarages broad and cleanly Streets, a ſpacious Market-Hill, fine and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Gardens and Orchards, within the Walls (while it was Beautified and honoured with their ſtanding.)
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101909:3"/>The Proſpect of it was very delightful from Queens-Croſs, which ſtands upon a Hill in <hi>London</hi>-Road, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a Mile diſtance from it. You come down from that Croſs to a Bottom, called <hi>Gotton-end,</hi> and from thence,<note place="margin">Of which ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Mr. <hi>Cambde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> paſſing a fair Stone-Bridg over the River <hi>Nen</hi> or <hi>Nine,</hi> you entred the Town on a flat, till you come within the South-Gate, and thence keeping the Northern-Road, you went out at the North-Gate, overcoming three Aſcents. The firſt in the Bridg-ſtreet, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſteep, but was made eaſie by the diverting ſight of good Buildings on either hand, and a neat Front on the top of that Street. You might obſerve the Town divided into Eaſt and Weſt; to the Weſt-Gate through the Gold-Street by St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church, to the Eaſt-Gate fetching a little compaſs by <hi>All-Hallows</hi> Church, through <hi>Abingdon</hi>-Street near St. <hi>Giles's Church.</hi> From the top of the firſt Aſcent, leaving on the right hand that great and well-built Church, <hi>All-Hallows,</hi> the chief in the Town, you come into the Drapery, a broad, and for the moſt part a well-built Street, and finely fronted with graceful Houſes; on the Right-hand of which, was one of the beſt open-Market-pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>England.</hi> This ſecond Aſcent was more eaſy and leiſurely than the former, and turning a little on the Left-hand, you went through the <hi>Sheep</hi>-Street, up a moderate Aſcent to the North-Gate, having St. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres</hi> Church on the Right-hand. By this Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Town, you imagine that it ſtood on a ſide of a Hill, facing the South-Sun, and that the middle, and loweſt part was ſheltered from the North-Wind: That it was divided into four Quarters, had four great Gates, <hi>Eaſt, Weſt, North</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> and had a Church in every Quarter, only <hi>All-Hallows</hi> ſtood Southward, and near the heart of the Town. The civil Diviſion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101909:4"/>of it was into five Wards, diſtinguiſhed from the four Winds or Quarters, and the fifth was the Chequer-Ward in the middle.</p>
            <p>And now I may ſay what, and more than the Men of <hi>Jericho</hi> ſaid to <hi>Eliſha;</hi> The Scituation is pleaſant, but the Water is naught and the Ground barren. <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton</hi> was Beautiful for the Scituation, the Water good, and the Ground about it rich. It ſtood above the River, which ran in the <hi>South,</hi> beating on both ſides upon very rich Meadow down quite to <hi>Peterbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row:</hi> And at which Gate ſoever you went out, you went out of a ſweet Town into a rich and noble Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion.</p>
            <p>But now (alas!) the Glory and Beauty of it,<note place="margin">overthrow.</note> is more than ſcorched with Fire, it is vaniſhed into Smoak. The great and goodly Church is become its own Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, and the Cellars the Graves and Pits into which the beſt contrived Dwellings are tumbled and hurried. It was a City upon a Hill, but now God hath turned it into a burning Beacon, to give warning to Towns and Cities of Judgments that may ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly invade them, and break in upon them, except they receive and obey his Laws, and ceaſe to provoke him, by their tolerated Diſobedience. God began with <hi>London,</hi> is come as far as <hi>Northampton</hi> to execure his Judgments, who knows whither he will Ride next in a Burning Charior, and where he will make an end? Were thoſe Citizens and theſe Townſmen ſinners above all Men? I tell you, Nay, but except you repent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Have not you your ſins alſo! yea, <hi>London</hi> ſins as rife as Faſhions! Nothing hath happened to them but what may be common to you, when ever God's forbearance is come up to an end. The Heart of <hi>London,</hi> and the Heart of <hi>Northampton,</hi> were Burnt out in the ſame
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101909:4"/>Month<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who can ſecure themſelves till <hi>September</hi> come about again from the ſame, or as great a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if you ſlight theſe Warnings?</p>
            <p>God who hath ſet the Bounds of our Habitations, hath ſet down with himſelf the Term of our Poſſeſſion of them. Every Man hath his appointed time, which takes in Means and Ways of coming to his ſtated Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod; ſo have Societies and Corporations of Men their appointed times; a time to Grow, and a time to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, (they are ſubject to Conſumptions and Feavers); thus ſtrong and high they ſhall grow in numbers of Men, and Proſperity; thus long they ſhall continue, and no longer. And what time ſoever God ſpeaks concerning a Nation, a City, a Palace, yea, a Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, to pluck up and pull down; he ſpeaks to the Fire, Burn, to the Wind, Blow, and carry it whither I will: Here it ſhall take, there burn, and here it ſhall ſtop.</p>
            <p>The utmoſt term that God would grant for <hi>Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> to continue as it was,<note place="margin">The Day.</note> was the <hi>Twentieth day of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,</hi> 1675. Hundreds of Inhabitants were turned out of their Houſes, upon a little or no Warning at all. To ſome the Sovereign Lord would not grant ſo much as leave to remove their Goods <hi>off his Ground;</hi> not ſo much as a Bed to lie on, or a Garment to ſhift them, not a Stool to ſit on, nor a Diſh to eat in. To others he was pleaſed to allow a few Hours (of Terror and Diſtraction) to remove and be gone; but he would not be entreated to give his deareſt Servants, not another Day, not that Night, no not that Afternoon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Means and Inſtruments, and Place where the Fire began.</note>God called for a ſtrong Weſt-wind to be ready at his Command, to carry a dreadful Fire whither he would have it. The unhappy Inſtrument of that Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was ſaid to be an infamous and common Woman, who lived in the end of St. <hi>Maries-ſtreet,</hi> next the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101909:5"/>Caſtle (in the Weſt.) The manner (thus, as I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed upon the place) ſhe had ſomething boyling on a Fire, and left the Fire careleſly, and went to the next Houſe; when ſhe had been there a little while, ſhe ſaid to her Companion, I will go and fetch my Child, and in a moment, finding her Houſe on fire, it ſeems took up her Baſtard, and ran out, and away, crying, <hi>I ſhall be Hang'd, I ſhall be Hang'd.</hi> She is not yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, nor found, to tell us what ſhe did. That Street was full upon the Wind, far from help, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal part of the Town, which was to be the Theatre of Judgment, and conſiſted of the poorer ſort of Houſes, Thatcht with Straw, fit matter to kindle a conſuming Fire.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The time of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Day.</note>The Fire brake out about half an hour paſt Eleven, came on directly to the back part of the Horſe-Market, ſtrengthening it ſelf with Ricks of Corn and Maltings, it ſpread out its Wing to the South, and lower end of that Market.<note place="margin">The Progreſs of it.</note> The hideous Cry of <hi>Fire, Fire,</hi> came up poſt to Town: but when ſome heard it was ſo far off, and in meaner Dwellings, they made the lighter of it, and others hoped it might ſpend it ſelf and go out, in a large Cherry-Ground, and other Orchards in the way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All-hallows</hi> Bells jangled their laſt and doleful Knell, preſently after the Chimes had gone Twelve in a more pleaſant Tune: And ſoon after the Wind which did flie ſwifter than Horſe-men, carried the Fire near the <hi>Dern-Gate,</hi> at leaſt half a Mile from the place where it began, and into St. <hi>Giles-ſtreet</hi> in the Eaſt, and conſumed every Houſe therein, ſave one (formerly a Gate-Houſe) whoſe end-Walls were higher than the Roof, and by them preſerved. When ſome that were ſtrong and active, ſaw the ſtreams of Fire driven be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101909:5"/>an impetuous Wind, ſeeing that nothing was like to ſtand before it, they made all haſte to ſhift for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to ſave their Goods. All hands and arms were full, all buſie in laying out, and miſlaying what they ſhall never ſee again. Some active Men did la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour all they could to ſave ſome Houſes; But what could be done in ſuch a ſudden Surprize? when ſo many Places were on Fire at once, and ſo many Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Buildings were as fuel dried, and laid in for this dreadful Fire.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Violence of the Fire.</note>Some that conſider not the confounding Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances that People were under, have been apt to caſt upon them the blame of Diſpair and Negligence: but they muſt be ſilent, when they believe upon the word of all I ſpake with, that all that's Burnt, was irreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibly gone in three Hours time; although I know that every Houſe was not Burnt in that time, for ſome few did not begin to Burn till Six a Clock at Night, but it was too ſtrong to be with-ſtood, and paſt hope of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaved by that time. Had it been a leiſurely Fire, proceeding in order of Houſes and Streets, then Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets might have quencht the Thirſt of a dry and greedy Element; then one Houſe might have been Blown up in Sacrifice, to have ſaved a Street: but this Fire would have ſcorned an Engine, nothing leſs than the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Windows in Heaven could have quencht its Rage. Houſes were caſually Blown up by Barrels of Powder, laid up for Sale, but the Fire kept up its Fury and its Way for all that. To talk now of Engins, and Blowing up of Houſes, are but Suppoſitions, which could not then preſerve a Houſe any more than now Rebuild one. We may as wiſely ſay, had it Rained all that day, the Town might have been ſaved from Burning.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101909:6"/>Diſtracted People! How buſie were they in empty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out their Goods, labouring to be before hand with the ſwift Deſtroyer, that came upon ſome of them, before their Fears had notice of it. The Fire was fled over the Town, but did not forget what it had to do, and therefore brake over the ſpacious planted Grounds, ſeiſed upon the <hi>Colledg-Lane,</hi> and finding there great quantities of Oyl and Tallow, and other combuſtible Matter, brake upon the back-ſide of the <hi>Drapery</hi> in a little time.<note place="margin">Care of Goods, but to little purpoſe.</note> Some threw their Goods into their Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; there or no where; ſome into the Church (that had more time and leiſure than the former) in which they were conſumed with it; Others into the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, and were there turned to Aſhes. The ſpacious Market-Hill was covered with all ſorts of Wares and Goods, theſe the affrighted Owners were forced to leave one among another, when they were encloſed with a Wall of Fire, and only one little Door of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeape left them to run out at, by Dr. <hi>Danver's</hi> Houſe, the only Houſe that ſtands in all that Row, having no Neighbour-dwelling to bear it company, nor Out-offices to ſerve its neceſſities, they being burnt, and it ſelf hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſerved. Some had better help, better coveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of Orchards and Cloſſes than others had; ſome more time than others, or elſe the Loſs had been vaſtly greater. And although the Fire ſpoiled and conſumed many Goods (it ſpared neither Croſs nor Pump, nor Timber drawn into the Market-place for the Seſſions-Houſe); yet what the Fire ſpared in that and other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>cruel Thieves,</hi> that come in to ſpoil the Spoiled, were more Mercileſs than a mercileſs Fire. May the ſtolen Sugars, Fruit, Spices, Linnen, Clothes, Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or what ever elſe theſe Men of Prey took by Fraud, be bitter, hot, cold, and uneaſie to them, till they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101909:6"/>have eaſed their Conſciences of ſo great a Guilt. But Divine Juſtice will take a Courſe with them, in a more dreadful Day than that was, except they Repent, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore, give Satisfaction, or be Forgiven.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Deſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of a help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs People de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</note>Sir, I know you can underſtand without my telling you, that this miſerable People were loth to leave their convenient and comfortable Dwellings, but more loth to loſe their Wares and Goods; but they were forced to leave the one to a Fire that would have them; and at laſt forced to leave both Houſe, and Shop, and Goods, to ſave their Lives. Give me leave to try, if I can make you ſenſible of their Condition, in a Dull and Miſty and Cold repreſentation of it: For a lively Image I cannot draw, becauſe my Boſom cannot hold their Paſſions, nor my Pen weep out their Tears. No words can report the Cries, Fears, Dangers, Diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Carefulneſs, and Amazedneſs of Young and Old, that doleful Day. Oh! the Roaring of Fire and Wind, what a Thunder in the Air! What Clouds of Smoak! What tearing cracks of Timber! Ancient Couples, Beams and Walls keeping cloſe to one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, till forced to part, ſuffering themſelves to be burnt Inch by Inch before they could be ſeparated! But what were theſe to the more ſenſible Out-crys of a People decreed to Ruine? If you will carry Wind and Flames and Burning-Houſes up and down to ſhew them, then and not before, will I undertake to relate what a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted Multitude thought, ſpeak, and did, who could not tell what to Think Speak or Do that might prove Succesful. There were old Men and Women, Children and Infants, Women lying-In, others full of the Small-Pox (which had been much in Town) Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that gave Suck. What could this helpleſs Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude do? Whither could they creep or run?— The
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101909:7"/>conſuming Fire it ſelf brought certain News that it was coming. The Fire and Wind, cried <hi>Fire,</hi> and did drown the Peoples Cries, and the hideous ſound of Bells.— Oh the confuſion of Language, Thoughts, and Actions of a ſurprized People! how quiet and ſecure were they but a little while before? Some were calling upon God, ſanctifying themſelves and all they had, committing Themſelves and their Affairs to Him; ſome preparing their Goods for <hi>London,</hi> others ready to ſit down to Dinner, and behold a Cry, <hi>Fire, Fire:</hi> Clouds of Smoak, Pillars and Sheets of Fire covering the Face of Heaven! Fire in the Weſt, that had left but few Houſes or Pieces to ſtand; Fire in the Eaſt that carried all before it, and in every Quarter, and the Body of the Town hemn'd in with Fire; and the ſtately Tower of the great Church turned into a Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, ſucking and drawing up the Fire and Smoak from within it, and diſcharging them out again in a mighty Body. What a ſight was this to have pleaſed a <hi>Nero?</hi> or ſuch as muſt be <hi>Roman,</hi> or think they are not <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a Change was here by five, by four, yea, by three and two of the Clock? How long are many Hands in rearing and adorning one Houſe? <hi>Northampton</hi> was raiſed to its late Perfection at the Expence of many Generations, one adding to another; but if the Great God ſpeak to the Fire, Burn, and to the Wind, Blow it a few Hours are time enough to Demoliſh it; How ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible is God in his Judgments? How impoſſible is it for me to feel my ſelf in the condition of a People ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, <hi>Ab Aris &amp; Focis,</hi> turned out of Doors, and as it were Excommunicated their Church? But whither were they gone? Into the Fields, and whither elſe they could, ſome one way, and ſome another. Great
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101909:7"/>was the care of People over little ones, and ſuch as could not well eſcape themſelves; and the waky Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence had diſpoſed of them in ſafety, though they knew not where to find one another. When the worſt was come, the Wife's Jointure, and the Child's Portion, and the Eſtate which was wont to maintain them, was exhauſted that Expenſive Day: how haſtily did they weave up and down, making inquiries after one another; ſome wanting words to tell you who they ſought for, and others at the ſame loſs to tell them tidings! How they looked and wrung their hands they themſelves cannot tell us now. What reſt could Parents take that Night, miſſing their Children? Some had wandred into neighbouring Villages, where they had never been before, and were not heard of till next day. Who can conceive the ſadneſs till they found out their Relations? And when they met, who can expreſs the Joy that they were alive? although many had not left them wherewith to refreſh them, feed them, cloath them, or wherein to lodg that Night. But God remembred Mercy! The Gentry who were preſerved in the Town, and near it, and others to their power, turned their Houſes into Inns and Hoſpitals and Ware-Houſes, to refreſh and comfort their diſtreſſed Neighbours. And now after that God had Smoaked them out, he was pleaſed to Hive them in, many Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies crouded into one Houſe; and eating that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the Fire had left of their ſtocks, till the compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Neighbourhood could ſend in Proviſions. And now having followed them from their own, into ſtrange and uneaſy Lodgings, I ſhut up my diſcourſe, and lead you to view the condition of that ruin'd Town as it was found next day.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101909:8"/>
               <note place="margin">How the Town looked next day.</note>Sir, had you ſeen the dreadful Fire that Night, you might have gueſſed what a place you were like to find it next Morning; but really, I could not have imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to be ſo ſoon reduced ſo unlike it ſelf! Next Morning you might have ſeen the late Dwellers come to ſee what was left them. Oh! how ſtrangely were they changed! Poor frighted, tired and amazed Men, how were their Faces changed! They looked as if they had come from under-Ground, out of Mines and Cole-Pits. They looked not only like Men that had loſt their Reſt, but ſpent with Cares and Faſting, ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Heat, and broken with Diſtractions! Dirty Faces, ſcalded Eyes, and their Eye-laſhes hung with Mortar made of Tears and Duſt blown into them. In the Afternoon you might ſee neither Town nor Towns-Men ſcarce, but Ruines inſtead of orderly Piles and Streets, and Strangers come into view them. The Inhabitants were gone, ſome to ſearch ſuſpitious Houſes for loſt Goods, others to get together ſome ends of ſomething that was left, or to ſeek out new Lodging for their afflicted Families; Others watching their Goods, till help could come to carry them away. Very few could tell me what was left, beſides their Lives, and a Charge to maintain.</p>
            <p>The firſt Obſervation I made, was upon the Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of Men, and I found them apt to Tears, ſenſible of the Hand of God, Calm, and thankful for their Lives.</p>
            <p>My next Obſervation was upon the Ruines, and when I have ſaid all I can ſay of them, 'tis this, that they were Ruines. Nothing ſtanding above the Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars that was combuſtible, which was not either burnt or burning down to Aſhes. No Timber left, from great Beams, even to Cheeks of Doors and and Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101909:8"/>When God compared his People to an uſeleſs Vine— Behold it is caſt into the Fire for Fuel,<note place="margin">Ezek 15.</note> the Fire devoureth both the ends of it, and the midſt of it is burnt: is it meet for any work? Even ſo did he uſe hundreds of Houſes, and the beſt in the principal Streets of <hi>Northampton:</hi> I hope he will deal graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the Men, and make them a fruitful Vine, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving prun'd and purg'd them. What was to be ſeen above Ground, but a few Fronts of Stone, Particion-Walls, and Chimnies? If you had no ſenſe but Eyes, you might think them to be Ruines of an ancient Date, but other Senſes would perſwade you they were but new, the Walls and Streets being glowing hot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this was noted to them on <hi>Michaelmas</hi> day (when the Mayor and Magiſtrates, as many as had a Gown, were in a colour ſuitable to their preſent condition, and not former State) that the upper Lintels were not left for the Cormorant and Bittern to lodg in, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>And for ſeveral reaſons, they who ſaw that Fire whoſe Epithite is, <hi>The Dreadful Fire of London!</hi> and this, do ſay, this was the more furious and deſtructive in its Proportion.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, in general, you may believe the Fire, and loſſes were very great: but if you will give me leave, I will ſhew you what made both ſo great. Firſt,<note place="margin">What made the loſs ſo great.</note> Firſt, the former years being bad for Carriage, and Fuel dear, they were almoſt out of Stock, till this good Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer came, and great plenty, at moderate Rates. This was a time to provide for this and another Winter. It was one part of the providence of <hi>Northampton</hi> Men, to lay in ſomething towards a wet and dear time, in a good Summer. They were cram'd full; and now what was laid up for future time, was conſumed in one day, before they had tam'd their Heaps.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101909:9"/>Secondly, As the Town was ful of Fuel, ſo Trades<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were full of Goods. They had newly furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves with the Commodities of <hi>Sturbridg</hi>-Fair. Beſides that, ſome had taken the advantages of the cheapneſs of all ſorts of Wares and Goods, and of Carriage, and laid out as far as their Stocks would reach, in hopes of a ſtirring Market: and many, if not all or moſt, had ſtored themſelves for their Winter-Trade. And as the Shopkeeper could not be fuller, ſo neither the Innkeeper, nor Husbandman: and ſuch as laid in their Crops for Malt, were very full; and none had any time to make returns. From this Conſideration ſome may readily infer, that others that gave them Credit muſt loſe, or hazard with then. This is not unlikely. But it will be found that the loſs is heavy upon them alone, and apart. For, 1. As few of them traded upon Credit, as any Town can be found to do. 2. Their Trade was but a home-Trade, (I except the Shoomaker and Hoſier) and wary and prudent Men could gueſs at the compaſs of it, and their prudence told them that the more Credit they had, the leſs profit they made. 3. As few Men failed and broke in <hi>Northampton,</hi> as in any Town of its Dimenſions, (and conſequently as few loſt by dealing with them.) A good argument of their dexterity, in ordering comparative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſmall Trade; to live ſo decently and plentifully as they did. 4. Many of them had plentiful Eſtates in Houſes, that brought in good Rent, and many li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in their own, whereby their Loſſes fall heavily up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves: but the wiſe God thought no leſs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Inſtrumental cauſes of this ſad Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, were the Drineſs of the Weather, the violence of the Wind, which was a ſwift Chariot for the All-ſubduing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101909:9"/>Fire, and it's to be noted, that God planted (pardon the impropriety) the Wind to blow up the heart of the Town, to which St. <hi>Maries</hi> Street ſtood level. And of that vehement Wind, 'tis to be obſerved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that it whirled the Fire at its pleaſure up and down; that it did alſo beat down the Smoak, and raiſe up the Duſt, which was a great diſcouragement of all endeavours to ſave the Town; and afflicted People<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They had Duſt to blind them, Smoak to ſtifle them, and Fire that ſindged and ſcorched them as they paſſed up and down. Sometimes it gave ſome hopes of ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, by turning two points North (as one Scholar tells me) but daſhed all again; by vereing to the Weſt. Another ingenious obſerver (who took care to ſave a Neighbour's Houſe near his own) tells me that the Fire fell upon the Thatch, ſtruck upon it, took it and danced for ſix minutes at leaſt, and by a ſudden turn the Wind carried it away, and with a little labour the Houſe eſcaped.</p>
            <p>Sir, If I have been too large in generals, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward your patience, by giving you ſatisfaction in the following particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The greatneſs of the Loſs, as given in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. The number of Houſes totally deſtroyed. 3. The influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of this loſs. 4. The relief. 5. The diſpoſal of it. Conclude with ſome few remarks.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">The Dammage.</note>1. The Loſs, as given in amounts to one hundred two thouſand and eight pounds odd mony, beſides the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the value of about fifty thouſand pound; a vaſt loſs, if we conſider how long an inland Town, that hath no manufacture in it, that drives none of the quickeſt Trades, is growing up, and how long they muſt needs be in regaining ſome part of it. To loſe the product of 20. or 30. years care and pains,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101909:10"/>both what was left them, and added by them, is a very great affliction. But the Lord gave before he took away. Hereby many in the middle part of their Lives, or the very latter end of their days, are ſent back to begin the World anew, or driven to end it in a low Eſtate.</p>
            <p>It may be an injury to others that ſome few are ſuſpected to give in their loſſes with a Cypher perhaps too much: if there be any ſuch, I heartily wiſh they would blot it out, leſt ſuch a Cypher eat out the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure: but again, it's verily thought, that others have been very ſcrupulous and ſparing. If Men cannot be diſproved, we ought to ſuſpend our Cenſures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The number of Houſes to tally conſumed, beſide Out-Houſes &amp;c. is about 600. wherein above 700. Families did dwell.<note place="margin">Numbers of Houſes.</note> And theſe Monuments of ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Mercy ſtand in the four Quarters of the Town, as the Arms and Legs drawn out in Torture, cut off from the Body; and it is as great a Wonder that here and there a Houſe ſhould eſcape, as that the reſt ſhould be brought to ruine in ſo ſhort a time. Some few Houſes remain near the Church, and only one Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Drapery, from the Street, hardly ſeen to the Street at this time. The chief Church in Town only burnt, the reſt untouched.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Influence and effects of this ſweeping Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fall upon many beſide the immediate Sufferers.<note place="margin">Effects.</note> 1. upon the Poor, which ſtood <hi>All-Hallows</hi> Pariſh in ten pound the Month, the Roll would have been raiſed to eleven pound this Winter. But now the Poor are multiplied, who, ſince the Fire fell into their Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (poor Creatures) lay within the Walls to the open Heavens (till now of late) except ſuch as got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Churches. Thither the Fire forced them, whither
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101909:10"/>God's Commands, nor Mercy nor Exhortations could invite them. A Judgment fitted to the ſin, a Judgment all Voice, as in other Inſtances.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Citizens will loſe their Cuſtomers, the Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man will loſe his Market, and the Landlord muſt fall his Rent, if <hi>Northampton</hi> be not relieved: yea more, many a Man muſt go further to ſeek for an honeſt Man to teach his Child a Trade; and many a one will want a ſervice, that cannot well be kept and maintained at home.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">Relief ſent in.</note>4. The Relief was conſiderable, as it was ſeaſonable to this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhed people. Many have told me, they found ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mercy and Compaſſion, and that they found more Friends, than ever they thought they had. The goodneſs of God and Men was admired. The kindneſs of a Nights Lodging, of a ſmall benevolence was magnified. The noble Earl of <hi>Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> who came that fatal Evening to ſee the Fire, was affected with the ſight, and ſent great ſtore of Proviſions the next day. many other perſons of Quality, Neighbour-Towns and Villages were very forward and generous. The bold and raking Poor had a glut, but the modeſt Houſe-Keeper looked pale and thin, till neceſſity overcame their modeſty, and then they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected.</p>
            <p>The Mayor ſent Meſſengers with Letters to intreat the Noble-Men and Gentlemen t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Town-Hall, to take their diſtreſſed condition into Conſideration. There appeared the Saturday following the dreadful Fire, the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Northampton;</hi> Recorder of the Town:<note place="margin">Relief ſent in. A Conſultation of the Noble-Men and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen.</note> three Lords; Sir <hi>Richard Rainsford,</hi> one of the Judges of the Kings-Bench. Seven or eight Baronets and Knights, and many Juſtices of the Peace and Gentlemen. The Meeting was principally managed by the Earl. The Reſult of all their Diſcourſes, was a Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to two Papers, to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We the Noble-Men and Gentlemen do promiſe to pay the ſeveral ſums ſet down over againſt, our Names,</hi> &amp;c. The one was to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Re-building of the Town, and the other was for the payment of Dr. <hi>Conant's</hi> Salary (which was 100 <hi>l. per Annum</hi>) and for the Relief of the Poor, and other uſes of the Town.</p>
            <p>They named <hi>Robert Haſlerig, William Tate, Henry Edmonds, Richard R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>insford</hi> Eſquines, Receivers and Treaſurers.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101909:11"/>Several Summs were gathered ſpeedily, upon the News of the Dreadful Fire, in ſeveral Corporations, by the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Cambridg,</hi> and already gathered, but not received, by the Univerſity of <hi>Oxon,</hi> Towns, Villages, and private Perſons: all which come to about 3000. Pound.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A diſtribution made.</note>Theſe ſeveral Sums of Mony were paid into the Hands of <hi>Robert Haſlerig</hi> 
               <abbr>Esq</abbr> living in Town. Who with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gentlemens conſent, made a very ſeaſonable Diſtribution of a great Sum among the Sufferers, wherein they had a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their Loſſes, to their Trades, and to their Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and diſability to go on. This was a timely Aſſiſtance given men, that were hard put to it to ſtrike up Sheds and Shops, and to take in ſome Winter-Proviſions. In this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution they deſigned to preſerve the Road, to bring in the Markes, to ſet Trade on Foot, to help the inferior Tradesmen. Beſides, they took Order to lay in a great Stock of Coal, to be ſerved out to the Inhabitants at their need in the approaching Winter. They disburſed Mony to the Officers of the Pariſh to pay their Poor. And laſtly, they have, and are fitting up Houſes for the Poor to live in, who had nothing left but bare Walls without a Roof.</p>
            <p>The Care, and Pains, and tenderneſs of theſe worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen deſerve the grateful acknowledgment of the diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sufferers; and indeed they ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o me to have an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſenſe, of the Mercy and Favour.</p>
            <p>I have been the more punctual in theſe things, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctify the Reporte of vaſt Sums ſaid to be flowing in, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many other Reaſons, to encourage liberal Souls to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Acts of Charity, when they ſee the Treaſury ſo well diſpenſed; both depoſited into, and diſpoſed by the hands of Perſons of Quality, Eſtate, and Integrity.</p>
            <p>There was about ſixty pound ſent from ſeveral Perſons of Quality, and others, to Dr. <hi>Conant,</hi> which was carefully diſtributed according to the intention of the Donors.</p>
            <p>The forward and noble beneficence of particular Perſons, and the kind and Chriſtian Expreſſion of Love made by Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Villages to <hi>Northampton</hi> brought low, though but a ſmall beginning to a great many,<note place="margin">Gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Town.</note> (nor the whole exceeding the loſs of ſome one or two Men) hath raiſed the Minds of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſo that there is hope in <hi>Northampton,</hi> but yet there
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101909:11"/>are many diſcouragements, that threaten the Life of it in ſome, and keep it from being over-joyful in the moſt chearful Temper.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe kindneſſes from Men. There are ſome eminent Providences which have brought kind Remembrances from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to a People under a diſpleaſure. The firſt is, that this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity is fallen upon them in a year of Plenty. Had it fallen upon them in one of the years paſt, many that were glad of a piece of Bread, muſt have periſhed for want of Bread. <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don Fire</hi> conſumed it, after a Plague, in a time of War, the Nation under Taxes: <hi>Northampton</hi> hath the odds in this, that ſhe is fallen, when a Nation may the better raiſe her up.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſweet and reviving providence is, that ſecond Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer which God was pleaſed to give us, He ſaid to an approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Winter, Keep off a while. He hath given a <hi>Midſummer</hi>-time after <hi>Michaelmas.</hi> He ſaid to the Sun, ſhine thou ſtill.</p>
            <p>What a Mercy hath this been to poor <hi>Northampton!</hi> By the favour of the Weather abundance of Coal came in, (even as far as <hi>Wedgbury,</hi> above fourty Miles) and as cheap as in Summer. A dreadful Fire had done enough to Starve them, conſuming their Stacks and Heaps; but the Sun continuing in its ſtrength relieved them, by bringing Firing to them, which I hope will be better ſpent. What the Fire deſtroyed, the Sun reſtored. Thus God doth correct and take into his Arms! Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Fury made quick riddance, but Mercy made haſte after them. Through the goodneſs of the Seaſon all ſorts of Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials for Buildings came whiſtling in (the Carter meeting with no Ruts nor Sloughs to put him out of Tune.) Yea, Deal scame down from <hi>London</hi> at as low or lower Rates than Country-Aſh. By this means Workmen came in, go on, not being beaten off with Weather.</p>
            <p>By this means raw Walls, new-Sawn and unſeaſon'd Boards, have been aired and ſeaſoned: by this means full Markets have come in, and the Market-Man hath not felt the inconvenience of a bad Standing for himſelf and Horſes.</p>
            <p>And Laſtly, by this means <hi>Northampton</hi> is brought up a little above its Ruines, and her New-Buildings to imitate <hi>Bartholomew</hi>-Fair. And in this Poſture I ſhall leave it, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heartily, that God would ſpeak to <hi>Northampton,</hi> It ſhall be built; and take pleaſure in the now diſtreſſed People, and their Poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:101909:12"/>
               <note place="margin">Obſervations upon the Fire.</note>And now, Sir, there remains but the laſt part of this Trouble, and I will relieve your Patience by a Concluſion, namely ſome Obſervations upon, or rather drawn from this Severe, but Righteous Providence, which ſpeaks to other Places with a loud Voice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It hath pleaſed God to ſtrike at all Conditions of Perſons, and all the Sins of the Town. He hath in great Mercy paſſed over the Houſes of many of the Gentry, who lived there for their own Pleaſure or Conveniency, which hath proved a great Relief to many of the Diſtreſſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Neighbours, but many of that Quality do alſo bear their ſhare of Loſs and Trouble: I deſire not to be Critical or Cenſorious. God took in all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Righteous and the Wicked fare alike, though for dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Ends: It hath happened to the Good, to make them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with a gracious Deſign, no doubt: And to the Wicked God ſaith, <hi>Why will you Die?</hi> He ſtretcheth out his Hand to them; but if they turn not, he hath whet his Sword, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Long-ſuffering of God, which waited but till the Flood, doth wait for their Repentance after the Fire. O that they would flie from Wrath to come! There were and are in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton</hi> good Figs, very good: (Such as obey every Ordinance of Man for the Lord's ſake, whether the King as Supreme, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such as feared God and wrought Righteouſneſs). But as the good Figs were to go to Captivity, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow theſe ſhall paſs through a Burning Furnace. And there were very naughty Figs, evil, very evil, that cannot be eaten. And ſo much the worſe, becauſe God came long expecting Fruit, having long been a Husbandman to it, and more eſpecially to that Pariſh, that is almoſt totally deſtroyed. God hath diminiſhed two other Pariſhes, (St. <hi>Peter's</hi> (Is it not a little one?) is <hi>ſpared entire</hi>) there was Iniquity in thoſe Skirts: But why God ſhould ſtretch out his Hand with a flaming Sword over <hi>All-hallows,</hi> more than others,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3.2.</note> I can give no other Reaſon, but that of the Prophet; You have I known of all the Families of the Earth, therefore will I Puniſh you for <hi>your Iniquities.</hi> They have been better Taught than others, and made the chief Pariſh in Town. God ſent to them Prophets, and Wiſe-Men, and Scribes, he hath been a Reprover of them all. Few Pariſhes perhaps (I am ſure I know but few) that have had ſuch Labourers as they for Five Succeſſions. Security, Luke-warmneſs, and bearing them that are Evil, are the Sins that God took worſe from Magiſtrates and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101909:12"/>People, than from other Towns. How hath the Spirit of God ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with them, and within this Year? They know the occaſion. And Fools that make a mock of Sin, may now believe, that God can be in Earneſt.— O Lord, Laugh not at their Calamity, who have ſet at naught thy Counſel, and would none of thy Reproof; and let them not be as Droſs in the Furnace.—</p>
            <p n="2">2. God hath dealt with <hi>Northampton</hi> in this Fire, mixing Mercy with Judgment, as in other Providences: Here is Mercy and Judgment, Patience and Fury. How ſhall I give thee up <hi>Ephraim?</hi> &amp;c. He hath made their Houſes like <hi>Adma;</hi> but to the People, he ſaith, Yet how ſhall I give thee up? Some that were fallen into Fellowſhip with groſs works of Darkneſs, had a long time of Languiſhing and Repentance, and gave Signs of it, diſcovered and warned others. But their Companions went on. How then? Have ſome eſcaped? What Execution hath God done in the Face of the World, in open Streets? Night-walking, boldneſs in Sin, Swearing and Drunkenneſs puniſhed in open Streets, by ſudden Death. Remember <hi>Lots</hi> Wife. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>S</hi>'s. <hi>F</hi>'s. <hi>O</hi>'s. Wife. There was Mercy, and here Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Of Conſorts and Companions, that Grind in the ſame Mill of Sin, one ſhall be taken, and another left.</p>
            <p n="3">3. From the unhappy Hand that kindled this Dreadful Fire, I obſerve, that they who eſcape deſerved Puniſhments, may be juſtly made the unhappy Inſtruments of puniſhing thoſe that ſhould have been juſtly ſevere with them. And it may give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to Magiſtrates, to look after the Skirts, the Back Lanes of their Towns, that Iniquity lodg not there.— The Cages of unclean Birds may bring whole Towns to Ruine.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is Marvellous that a Fire breaking out at Noon-day ſhould get ſo much ſtrength in ſo ſhort a time, conſume ſo many Goods and Houſes; yea, take away ſo many Lives,<note place="margin">Eight Perſons Burnt: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides two Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and a young Youth Killed by the fall of a ſtack of Chimneys ſince.</note>
               <hi>as Eight Perſons.</hi> And on the contrary, it ſeems to me a wonderful Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that ſo few periſhed in the Fire, when I conſider with what a mighty ſtream and force the Fire and Wind came on in ſome narrow Paſſages; that many People were Spent and Faint, their Spirits ſpent, their Eyes dazeled, or blinded with Duſt and Smoak; that ſome Houſes fell down when Perſons were run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by for Life; and that many had no other Paſſage open to fly for their Lives, but by venturing cloſe by raging Fire. And here I may add, what I received from a very worthy Friend, that he ſaw a Country-Fellow bring up a Barrel of Gun-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101909:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>out of an <hi>Apothecaries</hi> Cellar, when the <hi>Gold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and covering it with his Coat, went away with it in his Arms, which might have been his own Death, and the Death of many others.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whereas ſome may look upon this as caſually begun, and grown to ſo great a Miſchief by Over-ſights and Neglects of People, I cannot but ſee a great Plot of many conſpiring Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and all laid by the Holy, Juſt, Wiſe, and Abſolute Lord, both for Puniſhment, Correction, and Trial. I will Sum thoſe that readily occur. That the Wind ſhould fit ſo full upon that part of the Town, that the Fire ſhould kindle in a Street ſo combuſtible, far from Help ſpeedily to Suppreſs it, ſo Level upon the principal Places of the Town: That it ſhould flie ſo far as the Eaſt in a very little while; that the Heart of the Town ſhould be Environed, and Barricado'd with Flames, that there was no getting in no getting out for Teams, when they would have done moſt good, when the Shops and Houſes were moſt Emptied, and laid out of Doors, ready to be carried away. How eaſily might Teams have cleared the Market-Hill, and Church-yard, if the Four great Avenues and Paſſages had been paſſable? How little did many Towns think <hi>Northampton</hi> to ſtand in ſo much need of Help? Theſe and more being put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether make me Conclude, Is there Evil in the City, and the Lord hath not done it? God is known by the Judgments which he Executeth. <hi>Selah.</hi> Go ye now unto my Place which was in <hi>Shiloh,</hi> where I ſet my Name at the firſt, and ſee what I did to it, for the wickedneſs of my People <hi>Iſrael, Jer.</hi> 7.12.</p>
            <p>And now, Sir, becauſe I ſaid I will conclude, I will inſtead of making an Apologie for my ſelf, Why ſo late? Why ſo long? Or to others why ſo ſhort? Or why I? I will only ſay, that I have ſome feeling of the Sufferings of my worthy and dear Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, pray it may riſe higher and better, that I hope your Intereſt and Endeavours may do good, that I have endeavoured to make their deplorable Condition to ſpeak for them, and that I owe you a far greater Service, when you ſhall command it, if I can perform it. For I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Obliged Servant. <hi>E. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
